Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 PE.016
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Automobile Workers of America, District 65
1950-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.016
3.1 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 3 shared boxes, and 1 flat file folder
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) (1883-1992) is an artificial collection of materials assembled by the Tamiment Library, which was founded in 1906 as the library of the Rand School of Social Science, and is a special collection documenting the history of United States radicalism, labor, and progressive social action. Tamiment Library staff accumulated printed ephemera through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, organizations, bookstores, and other collecting activities. The organization that is now District 65 was created to organize wholesale, retail, and office workers, and was affiliated with several unions before affiliating with the United Auto Workers in 1969. The collection contains materials created by District 65 and its subsidiaries, including committee files, agreements, constitutions, circular letters, and pension plans.
Historical Note
The labor union now known as District 65, UAW, was organized in 1933, by Arthur Osman and in 1938 became Local 65 of the United Retail and Wholesale Employees of America, CIO. In 1948, Local 65's leadership refused to sign the Taft-Hartley Act's non-communist affidavits, and Local 65, seceded from its parent union and the CIO but rejoined in 1954 as District 65 of the RWDSU (Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union). In 1969, differences, including the union's opposition to the Vietnam War, led to District 65's disaffiliation from the RWDSU and the formation of the National Council of Distributive Workers of America. In 1979, District 65 joined the United Automobile Workers. Though at first primarily composed of Jewish workers, the union expanded to include persons of various geographical and ethnic backgrounds from the retail and manufacturing sectors, clerical personnel, salesclerks, writers, editors, technicians, and lawyers. The collection contains minutes, shop files, arbitrations, grievances, counsel files, membership information and reports, financial material, and the records of some of the unions that were affiliated with District 65 throughout its history.
In February of 1950, an international that was to be one of the shortest-lived unions in American labor history came into being. This was the Distributive Workers Union (DWU), formed by a merger of local 65 and other former Retail and Wholesale affiliates: Local 2 (Gimbels-Saks 34th Street); Local 3 (Bloomingdales); Local 5 (Sterns); Local 1199 (Drug Clerks); and Local 144 (Displaymen). Local 1250, formerly affiliated with the Retail Clerks International and representing the Norton's department stores employees and Local 121, formerly part of the Gas, Coke and Chemical workers also merged. Local 65 had 122 of the 290 delegates to which the various merging locals were entitled. Arthur Osman headed the international; David Livingston became president of Local 65. In April, 1950, Local 65 leaders signed the non-communist affidavits in order, they said, to minimize the danger that other unions would use the NLRB facilities against the DWU's proposed organizing campaign.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Oral History Collection (OH 19)
United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Records (WAG 6)
Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union, Local 1-S, Department Store Workers Union (WAG 12)
Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union, Local 3, United Store Workers (WAG 230)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of agreements, constitutions, newspapers clippings and publications relating to District 65 in various unions. Locals representing department store employees and university staff are found throughout the collection. Strikes by department stores workers are documented in the files as are general activities of the unions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
I. General Files, 1950-1984
II. Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America, 1950-1979
III. Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, 1951-1978
IV. United Auto Workers, 1979-1990
V. Wholesale, Retail, Office and Processing Union, 1952-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession numbers NPA.2001.068 and NPA.2001.043 are associated with this colleciton.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Fliers (printed matter); Memorandums.; Circulars (fliers); Constitutions.; Collective labor agreements.; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union. Local 1-S Department Store Workers Union (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works
- Series I: General Files, 1950-1984; 1.1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 flat file folder
  - Agreements, 1950-1974 (Box 1)
  - Art Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - General, undated (Box 1)
  - Local 3 (Bloomingdales), undated (Box 1)
  - Local 5 (Independent), undated (Box 1)
  - Local 1499, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Peace Action Committee I, 1964-1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Peace Action Committee II, 1964-1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Poly Local, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Timeline: A History of Democratic Unionism, undated (Flat-file-folder 8)
  - Yale Federation of University Employees, 1984 (Box 1)
- Series II: Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America, 1950-1979; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Agreement: Revlon, Inc., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Articles about, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Barnard College, 1972-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Bell Telephone Local, 1970-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Black Affairs Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters I, undated (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters II, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1975-1976, undated (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 3)
  - Concord Fabrics Strike, 1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Convention, 1972, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Facts, History, undated (Box 1)
  - Hearn Department Stores Strike, 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Hofstra University Institute of Applied Social Science, 1976-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Legal Workers Unions, undated (Box 1)
  - Livingston, David, 1946-1953 (Box 2)
  - Membership Book, undated (Box 2)
  - National Association of Women's and Children's Apparel Salemen (NAWCAS); Wholesale Apparel Salesmen's Local, 1965-1973 (Box 2)
  - New York University, 1975-1976, undated (Box 2)
  - Paley, Jack, 1946-1953 (Box 2)
  - Prisoner's Union, 1972, undated (Box 2)
  - Progressive Labor Party, undated (Box 2)
  - Publishing Division, 1969-1978, undated (Box 2)
  - Stewards, undated (Box 2)
  - Temple Local, undated (Box 2)
  - Women's Committee, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Workers Action Committee, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, 1951-1978; 1 linear foot in 1 record carton
  - Agreements, 1962-1974 (Box 2)
  - Circular Letters, undated (Box 2)
  - Demonstration and Training Project materials, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Local 2, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Local 144 (Displaymen), 1952 (Box 2)
  - The Senior 65er, 1976, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Security Plan (benefits), 1951-1959 (Box 2)
  - Security Plan (Benefits), 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - Security Plan (Benefits), 1973-1979 (Box 2)
  - Stewards Kit, undated (Box 2)
- Series IV: United Auto Workers, 1979-2002; 1.75 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 2 shared boxes
  - 1979-1985 (Box 2)
  - 1984-1986, undated (Box 2)
  - undated (Box 2)
  - Boston University, undated (Box 2)
  - Columbia University, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1980-2002 (Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 2)
  - General Motors Strike, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Hofstra University, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
  - Eighth Street Bookshop (New York, NY), undated (Box 2)
  - Harper and Row, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Legal Division, 1988, undated (Box 2)
  - New York Historical Society, 1980, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1967-1992, undated (Box 2, Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 184, Folder 31)
  - Reports, 1976-1979 (Box Shared Tamiment 192, Folder 4)
  - Security Plan, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - Technical Office Professionals, undated (Box 2)
- Series V: Wholesale, Retail, Office and Processing Union, 1952-1974; 1 linear foot in 1 record carton
  - Agreement: Metropolitan Container Council, Inc., 1968 (Box 2)
  - Constitution, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Constitution, 1974 (Box 2)
  - General, 1970, undated (Box 2)
  - Pension Plan, 1969 (Box 2)